Brian Libgober

School of Global Policy and Strategy University of California, San Diego blibgober@ucsd.edu +1 708 642 4741 brianlibgober.com

RESEARCH SUMMARY

My research focuses on the political economy of American institutions. Regulation-making by executive agencies is a particular focus. While the majority of American political scientists working on regulation focus on issues of separation of powers, political control, and oversight, my work focuses on the relationship between regulators and lobbyists. This focus connects with my broader interest in the relationship between economic inequality, interest group power, and the design of legal and governmental institutions. Methodologically, I combine multiple approaches, including formal models, quantitative empirics, and case studies.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Government, Harvard University, 2018

M.A. Statistics, Harvard University, 2017

J.D. University of Michigan Law School, cum laude, 2015

B.A. Mathematics and Philosophy, University of Chicago, *with honors*, 2010.

APPOINTMENTS

2020 – University of California, San Diego

Assistant Professor, School of Global Policy and Strategy

2018–20 Yale University

Postdoctoral Associate, Department of Political Science

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-Reviewed Publications

"Strategic Proposals, Endogenous Comments, and Bias in Rulemaking." *The Journal of Politics*. DOI: 10.1086/706891. Brian Libgober.

"Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Rulemaking." *Quarterly Journal of Political Science*. DOI: 10.1561/100.00018135. Brian Libgober.

"Data and methods for analyzing special interest influence in rulemaking." *Interest Groups and Advocacy*. DOI: 10.1057/s41309-020-00094-w. Daniel Carpenter, Devin Judge-Lord, Brian Libgober, and Steven Rashin.

Working Papers

- 2021 Carpenter2021
- "Making Regulators Reasonable: Do Procedural Rationality Requirements Fix Cognitive Biases?" Benjamin Minhao Chen and Brian Libgober.
- "Personnel, Politics, and the Trump Presidency." Brian Libgober and Mark D. Richardson.
- "The Political Ideologies of Organized Interests & Amicus Curiae Briefs: Large-Scale, Social Network Imputation of Ideal Points." Sahar Abi-Hassan, Janet M. Box-Steffensmeier, Dino P. Christenson, Aaron R. Kaufman, and Brian Libgober.
- "Linking Datasets on Organizations Using Half A Billion Open Collaborated Records."

 Connor Jerzak and Brian Libgober.
- 2020 "Agency Failure and Individual Accountability." Brian Libgober.

Work In Progress

- "Ex Post Lobbying and the Dynamics of Legislative Attention." Brian Libgober.
- "Participatory Inequality and Rulemaking: Evidence from Financial Regulation."

 Brian Libgober, Susan Webb Yackee, Daniel P. Carpenter, Steven Rashin, Devin Judge-Lord,
 Jacob Waggoner, and Chris Kenny.
- "Lobbying, Cheap Talk, and Norms of Aggregation." Chris Li and Brian Libgober.
- "The Politics of Place: Evidence from Refugees to the U.S.." Valentin Bolotnyy, Mayya Komisarchik, and Brian Libgober.

Other Publications

- "Getting a Lawyer While Black: A Field Experiment." Lewis & Clark Law Review. DOI: 10.2139/ssrn.3389279. Brian Libgober.
- "Can the EU be a Constitutional System Without Universal Access to Judical Review?"

 Michigan Journal of International Law. Brian Libgober.

INVITED TALKS

- 2020 "Agency Failure and Individual Accountability," Georgetown University, Jan 24.
- "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," University of Texas, Austin, Jan 8.
- "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Stanford University (Hoover Institution), Dec 6.
- "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Vanderbilt University, Nov 13.
- "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," University of California San Diego (GPS), Nov 6.
- "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Harvard Law School, Nov 5.
- 2019 "Agency Failure and Individual Accountability," George Mason Law School, Sep 19.

- "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Washington University in St. Louis, Sep 17.
- "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Berkeley Law School, Feb 7.
- "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Harvard Business School, Nov 5.
- "The Gains from Lobbying Financial Regulators," Administrative Conference of the United States, Aug 9.
- "What's at Stake in Rulemaking? Financial Market Evidence for Banks' Influence on Administrative Agencies," University of Texas, Austin, Mar 23.

Departmental Talks

- "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Political Economy Workshop, Harvard University, Oct 29.
- "What Public Comments During Rulemaking Do (and Why)," American Politics Research Workshop, Harvard University, Feb 13.
- "Getting a Lawyer While Black: A Field Experiment," Working Group in Political Psychology, Harvard University, Mar 10.
- "Lawyering and Lobbying: Why Banks Shape Rules," American Politics Research Workshop, Harvard Government, Feb 7.
- "Getting a Lawyer While Black: A Field Experiment," Harvard Experiments Working Group, Harvard Government, Sep 9.
- "Getting a Lawyer While Black: A Field Experiment," Law and Economics Seminar, Harvard Law School, Mar 3.

CONFERENCE ACTIVITY

Conference Presentations

- "The Politics of Place: Evidence from Refugees to the US," American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference, Oct 2).
- "Ex Post Lobbying and the Dynamics of Legislative Attention," American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference, Oct 1.
- "Participatory Inequality and Rulemaking: Evidence from Financial Regulation," American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference, Sep 30).
- "One Voice: the Role of Organization in Lobbying," American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference, Sep 10.
- "Agency Failure and Individual Accountability," Bureaucracy and Presidential Administration: Expertise and Accountability in Constitutional Government, George Mason Law School, Dec 6.
- "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," American Law and Economics Association (ALEA) Annual Conference, May 17.

- "Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Southern Political Science Association (SPSA) Annual Conference, Jan 18.
- "What Public Comments During Rulemaking Do (and Why)," Midwest Political Science Association (MPSA) Annual Conference, Apr 7.
- "The Price of Votes," Midwest Political Science Association (MPSA) Annual Conference, Apr 5.
- "What Public Comments During Rulemaking Do (and Why)," Southern Political Science Association (SPSA) Annual Conference, Jan 5.
- "Participation, Inequality, and Rational Responsiveness," Southern Political Science Association (SPSA) Annual Conference, Jan 4.
- "Lobbying with Lawyers: Financial Market Evidence for Banks' Influence on Rulemaking," Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study, Dec 8.
- "Equities and Inequities in Financial Rulemaking," Midwest Political Science Association (MPSA) Annual Conference, Apr 6.
- "Lawyering and Lobbying: Why Banks Shape Rules," University of Chicago Booth Business School, Mar 4.
- "Accident Liability in Imperfectly Competitive Markets," American Law and Economics Association (ALEA) Annual Meeting, May 16.

Poster Sessions

"Meetings, Comments, and the Distributive Politics of Administrative Policymaking," Annual Conference on Empirical Legal Studies (CELS), Nov 9.

Other Conference Participation

- "Lobbyists and Lobbying, Strategies and Goals," American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference, Oct 3 (discussant).
- "Politics of Rulemaking in the Administration State," American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference, Oct 1 (discussant).
- "Legislative Productivity in the US," American Political Science Association (APSA)
 Annual Conference, Sep 29 (chair and discussant).
- "Separation of Powers and Interbranch Relationships," American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference, Sep 30 (chair and discussant).
- "Advances in Law Enforcement Policy Research," American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference, Sep 30 (chair).

GRANTS, AWARDS, AND FELLOWSHIPS

- 2016-18 Stone PhD Scholar in Inequality and Wealth Concentration, Harvard Kennedy School.
- 2015 Terence M. Considine Fellowship in Law and Economics.
- 2012-15 Dean's Scholarship (Partial Tuition), University of Michigan Law School.
- 2006-10 Viola Bower Merit Scholarship (Full Tuition), University of Chicago.

TEACHING

University of California San Diego

- 2021 Policy Analysis and Social Welfare (MPP/MIA). Primary Instructor. Fall.
- Law and Administration (MPP/MIA). Primary Instructor. Fall.
- Law and Administration (MPP/MIA). Primary Instructor. Spring.
- Bureaucratic Politics (MPP/MIA). Primary Instructor. Spring.
- Interest Groups and the Policymaking Process (MPP/MIA). Primary Instructor. Winter.

Yale University

- American Mass Media: Law, Politics, and Policy (Undergraduate). Primary Instructor. Fall.
- 2019 Money in Politics (MPP/MIA). Primary Instructor. Spring.

Harvard University

- Formal Models of Domestic Politics (PhD). Teaching Assistant (Primary Instructor: Horacio Larreguy). Fall.
- Bureaucratic Politics (Undergraduate/Graduate). Teaching Assistant (Primary Instructor: Daniel Carpenter). Fall.

Massachussets Institute of Technology

2015 Constitutional Law & Judicial Politics (PhD). Course Assistant (Primary Instructor: Chris Warshaw). Spring.

University of Michigan

Mass Media and Election Politics (Undergraduate). Graduate Student Instructor (Primary Instructor: Nicholas Valentino). Fall.

DEPARTMENTAL SERVICE

University of California San Diego

2021- Law and Policy Ad Hoc Exploratory Committee.

2020- Admission's Committee.

Harvard University

2015-17 Graduate Student Coordinator, Undergraduate Research Scholars Program, Institute for Quantitative Social Science.

Academic Journal Peer Review

American Political Science Review

JPART

The Journal of Politics

American Journal of Political Science

Politics & Gender

MEMBERSHIPS

American Political Science Association Midwest Political Science Association Southern Political Science Association American Law and Economics Association

PROFESSIONAL EMPLOYMENT

Summer Associate. Paul Hastings LLP. New York, NY.

Summer Law Clerk to Chief Judge Beryl Howell. US District Court, Washington, DC.

2011-12 Polling Analyst. Obama for America. Chicago, IL.

Updated August 2021